Register of the Stanford Listening Post Records, 1940-1945
Hoover Institution Archives
Stanford Listening Post Records,
1940-1945
40001
Stanford Listening Post
32 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope. 13.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, transcripts of radio broadcasts, study papers, notes, and card indexes, relating to radio broadcasts from east and southeast Asia
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1940.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Office of War Information; Propaganda; Radio broadcasting--East Asia; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda; East Asia; United States
Historical Note
The Stanford Listening Post was established in the Archives Division of the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace in 1940 for the purpose of recording and studying radio broadcasts from the Far East. The Rockefeller Foundation granted $8,250 to cover the costs of equipment, supplies, and salaries for receiving, recording, and transcribing trans-Pacific broadcasts. Recording began in mid-September 1940 and continued to the end of May 1941 when the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) established listening posts throughout the country for round-the-clock monitoring of foreign broadcasts. The Stanford post recorded foreign broadcasts for the FCC from 1941 to 1943 and transmitted American broadcasts of the United States Office of War Information (OWI) to the Far East from 1942 to 1945.
The Stanford Listening Post used two short-wave receivers, an RME 69 and a highly selective HRO. During the last few weeks of the experiment, a Hallicrafter commercial type receiver was used in place of the RME. Two rhombic antennas provided directional reception from east-west and north-south. Two standard office Ediphones recorded the broadcasts. Only transmissions in English were recorded in the beginning, although test recordings of other languages were made. News and news commentator programs in English from three stations were recorded regularly--Tokyo, Japan; Chungking, China; and Saigon, French Indo-China. Occasional recordings were made from Hsinking, Manchukuo; Shanghai, China; and Sydney, Australia.
After broadcasts were recorded on Ediphone wax cylinders, a single typed copy was made of the transcript with text double spaced. There were several checks for accuracy. After the final checking, transcripts were duplicated and sent to a selected list of persons and libraries interested in Pacific affairs.
The staff of the Stanford Listening Post included Inez G. Richardson, who was director, Richard Beckett, Pauline Hamm, Maria Hoge, Rosemary Johansson, Kay Kitagawa, Margaret Lintner, Helene von Damm, and Ann Van Wagenen.
(Source: Annual Report of the Chairman, 1940-41. Hoover Library on War, Revolution, and Peace).
Series Description
- Card Indexes. (Box Box No. 1.-2.)
  Three card files consisting of a list of subscribers to the Stanford Listening Post transcripts, a reference file to general information used by Stanford Listening Post staff, and a subject index to the Stanford Listening Post transcripts (citations are to the Tokyo-to-America broadcasts unless otherwise stated). Each file is arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Correspondence, 1941, 1959. (Box Box No. 3.)
  Correspondence relating to subscription of the Stanford Listening Post transcripts, arranged chronologically.
- Transcripts of Broadcasts Received, 1940-1943. (Box Box No. 3.-14.)
  Transcripts of foreign broadcasts received by the Stanford Listening Post, September 1940 to May 1941, and transcripts of foreign broadcasts received by Stanford on behalf of the U.S. Office of War Information (OWI) and the Federal Communications Commission (FCC), June 1941 to June 1943. Folders include draft translations as well as final transcripts. Arrangement is alphabetical by transmitting city and there-under chronological. The transcripts of the Tokyo broadcasts are divided into three groups--broadcasts intended for the Americas, broadcasts intended for Asia, and broadcasts received by Stanford on behalf of OWI and FCC.
- Transcrips of OWI Broadcasts Transmitted, 1942-1945. (Box Box No. 15.-21.)
  Transcripts of broadcasts originating with the Office of War Information (OWI) and transmitted from Stanford by short-wave radio to the Far East. Arranged alphabetically by names of the OWI news services and there-under chronologically. The OWI news services included the Chinese News (sometimes called the Chinese Dialect News or Dialect News), Japan-Formosa News, and Thai News.
- Project to Analyse Foreign Broadcasts Received by the Stanford Listening Post, 1940-1942. (Box Box No. 22.-29.)
  Correspondence, drafts of study papers, outlines and plans, notes, and broadcast transcripts of a project to study and compare the propaganda methods of China and Japan as revealed in their radio broadcasts. The final report was not completed, but the records contain drafts of some chapters, notes and copies of Stanford Listening Post broadcast transcripts arranged by subject.
Container List
- Card Indexes
  - List of subscribers to transcripts (Box 1.)
  - Subject index to transcripts (citations are to Tokyo-to-America broadcasts unless otherwise stated)
  - Reference file to information on important persons in the news, foreign words and idioms, and foreign newspapers (Box 2.)
- Correspondence, 1941, 1959.
  - Correspondence relating to subscriptions to Stanford Listening Post transcripts (Box 3.)
- Transcripts of Broadcasts Received, 1940-1943
  - Chungking, September 15, 1940-February 28, 1941 (Box 3.)
  - Chungking, March 1, 1941-May 15, 1941 (Box 4.)
  - Chungking, May 16, 1941-May 31, 1941 (Box 5.)
  - Chungking, March 1941-April 1941 (second copy)
  - Chungking, July 1941-August 1941 (OWI-FCC)
  - Hsinking (Manchukuo), August 1941 (OWI-FCC)
  - Saigon, September 15, 1940-October 15, 1940
  - Saigon, October 16, 1940-February 28, 1941 (Box 6.)
  - Saigon, March 1, 1941-May 15, 1941 (Box 7.)
  - Saigon, May 16, 1941-May 30, 1941 (Box 8.)
  - Saigon, August 1941 (OWI-FCC)
  - Sydney, February 1, 1941-May 31, 1941
  - Tokyo-America, September 15, 1940-September 30, 1940
  - Tokyo-America, October 1, 1940-December 31, 1940 (Box 9.)
  - Tokyo-America, January 1, 1941-March 31, 1941 (Box 10.)
  - Tokyo-America, April 1, 1941-May 30, 1941 (Box 11.)
  - Tokyo-Asia, September 15, 1940-November 30, 1940
  - Tokyo-Asia, December 1, 1940-May 31, 1941 (Box 12.)
  - Tokyo, June 1941-September 1941 (OWI-FCC)
  - Tokyo, August 1941-September 1941 (OWI-FCC) (Box 13.)
  - Thailand, September 1942-February 1943 (OWI-FCC)
  - Thailand, March 1943-June 1943 (OWI-FCC) (Box 14.)
  - Miscellaneous transcripts (Stanford Listening Post)
- Transcripts of OWI Broadcasts Transmitted, 1942-1945
  - Chinese News, August 1942-March 1943 (Box 15.)
  - Chinese News, April 1943-September 1943 (Box 16.)
  - Chinese News, October 1943-March 1944 (Box 17.)
  - Chinese News, April 1944-September 1944 (Box 18.)
  - Chinese News, October 1944-November 1944 and January 1945-April 1945 (Box 19.)
  - Chinese News,May 1945-August 1945 and miscellaneous broadcasts (Box 20.)
  - Japan-Formosa News, May 1945-August 1945
  - Thai News, May 1942-June 1943 (Box 21.)
- Project to Analyse Foreign Broadcasts Received by Stanford Listening Post, 1940-1942
  - Project correspondence, 1942 (Box 22.)
  - Outlines and plans
  - Chapter outlines
  - Project report--outlines, introduction to Chungking chapter, resume of propaganda content
  - Project report, drafts
    - Comparison of Chungking and Tokyo broadcasts
    - Comparisons of press
    - Chungking broadcasts
    - Quantitative tables comparing broadcast references to subjects
    - Tabulated analysis of references to leaders
  - Subject arrangement of transcripts, 1940-1942
    - Burma Road
    - China
      - Agriculture
      - Communism
      - Education
      - French Indo-China relations
      - General
      - Government control of economics
      - Government development of economics
      - Health (Box 23.)
      - Industrial cooperatives
      - Military failures
      - Monetary policy
      - Morale
      - Occupation of
      - Overseas Chinese
      - Pleas for American aid
      - Political developments
      - Radio communications
      - Relief program
      - Shanghai, international settlement
      - Transportation and communications
      - War (Chungking broadcasts only)
    - European War (Box 24.)
    - France (Box 25.)
      - Collaboration with Axis
      - International policy
      - Marshal Petain
    - French Indo-China and Thailand
      - Radio Saigon
      - Saigon
    - Germany
    - Great Britain (Box 26.)
      - Pro-British broadcasts
      - Anti-British broadcasts
      - Anglo-Soviet relations
    - Japan
      - Balkan relations
      - Chungking bombings
      - Culture, education, and research
      - Dutch East India relations
      - Economy
      - Economic expansion
      - Expansion
      - Foreign travellers
      - German relations
      - Imperial way
      - Indo-China penetration (Box 27.)
      - Italian relations
      - Morale
      - Occupation of China
      - Peace offensive
      - Political reorganization
      - South American relations
      - Special references
      - Triparte Pact
      - U.S. relations
      - War (Tokyo broadcasts only)
    - Russia
      - Chinese relations
      - Japanese relations
    - United States (Box 28.)
      - American evacuation
      - Anti-American propaganda
      - Pro-American propaganda
      - Placating American public opinion
    - War stories
    - Unindexed transcripts
    - Unindexed transcripts (Box 29.)
  - Miscellaneous project notes
    - Australia (Box 30-32.)
    - China
    - Indo-China
    - Tokyo-America
    - Tokyo-Asia